Today, I am going to show you
اليوم , سأعرض لكم
how this tablet and this virtual-reality headset that I'm wearing
كيف أن هذا التابلت و سماعة الواقع الإفتراضي التي أرتديها
are going to completely revolutionize science education.
ستحدث ثورة كاملة في تعليم العلوم.
And I'm also going to show you
أيضاَ سأريكم
how it can make any science teacher more than twice as effective.
كيف ستجعل أي مدرس علوم أكثر فعالية بأضعاف.
But before I show you how all of this is possible,
ولكن قبل أن أريكم كيف أن كل هذا ممكن،
let's talk briefly about why improving the quality of science education
دعونا نتحدث بإيجاز لماذا تطويرجودة تعليم العلوم
is so vitally important.
هو في غاية الأهمية.
If you think about it,
إذا فكرنا بهذا الشيء،
the world is growing incredibly fast.
العالم ينمو بشكل متسارع.
And with that growth comes a whole list of growing challenges,
و ياتي مع ذلك النمو قائمة كاملة من التحديات المتزايدة،
challenges such as dealing with global warming,
تحديات مثل التعامل مع الاحتباس الحراري،
solving starvation and water shortages
حل المجاعات و نقص الماء
and curing diseases,
وعلاج الأمراض،
to name just a few.
على سبيل المثال لا الحصر.
And who, exactly, is going to help us solve all of these great challenges?
و من هو بالضبط الذي سيساعدنا في حل كل هذه التحديات الكبرى؟
Well, to a very last degree, it is these young students.
حسناَ هؤلاء الطلاب الصغار.
This is the next generation of young, bright scientists.
هذا هو الجيل القادم من الشباب والعلماء المشرقين.
And in many ways, we all rely on them
و نحن جميعاَ نعتمد عليهم، بعدة طرق
for coming up with new, great innovations
لتقديم الإبتكارات الجديدة العظيمة
to help us solve all these challenges ahead of us.
لمساعدتنا في حل كل هذه التحديات التي تواجهنا .
And so a couple of years back,
وحتى بضع سنوات سابقة،
my cofounder and I were teaching university students just like these,
معلميني و أنا كنا ندّرس طلاب الحامعة هكذا،
only the students we were teaching looked a little bit more like this here.
والطلاب الذي كنا ندرسهم كانوا يبدو بطريقة ما هكذا .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And yes, this is really the reality out there
نعم،هذه الحقيقة هناك،
in way too many universities around the world:
بطريقة ما بالعديد من الجامعات حول العالم:
students that are bored, disengaged
الطلاب هناك يشعرون بالملل وعدم الإهتمام،
and sometimes not even sure why they're learning about a topic
و في أحيان أخرى هم في شك عن سبب تعلمهم مثل هكذا موضوع
in the first place.
في المقام الأول.
So we started looking around for new, innovative teaching methods,
لذا بدأنا بالبحث عن مبادئ جديدة، مبتكرة في التدريس،
but what we found was quite disappointing.
ولكن ما وجدناه كان مخيباَ للآمال تماماَ.
We saw that books were being turned into e-books,
رأينا أن الكتب قد تم تحويلها إلى كتب إلكترونية،
blackboards were being turned into YouTube videos
السبورات قد جرى تحويلها إلى أشرطة فيديو يوتيوب
and lecture hall monologues were being turned into MOOCs --
مشاهد قاعة المحاضرة قد تم تحويلها الى مساقات تعليم عبر الانترنت
massive online open courses.
دورات تعليمية ضخمة عبر الأنترنت.
And if you think about it,
وإذا فكرنا في هذا،
all we're really doing here is taking the same content
كل ما نقوم به حقاَ هنا هو أخذ نفس المحتوى
and the same format,
و نفس الشكل،
and bringing it out to more students --
والوصول بها إلى عدد أكبر من الطلاب -
which is great, don't get me wrong, that is really great --
وهو أمر عظيم، لا تفهموني خطأ، وهذا شيء عظيم حقاَ -
but the teaching method is still more or less the same,
ولكن طريقة التدريس لاتزال بشكل أو بآخر نفسها،
no real innovation there.
لا تحوي أي إبداع حقيقي .
So we started looking elsewhere.
لذلك بدأنا بالبحث في مكان آخر.
What we found was that flight simulators had been proven over and over again
ما وجدناه أن أجهزة محاكاة الطيران قد ثبت مراراَ و تكراراَ
to be far more effective
بأنها قد تكون أكثر فعالية
when used in combination with real, in-flight training to train the pilots.
عندما نستخدم الجمع بين التدريب الحقيقي و في أجواء الطيران لتدريب الطيارين،
And so we thought to ourselves:
وهكذا كنا نفكر بأنفسنا:
Why not just apply that to science?
لماذا لانطبق ذلك في العلوم؟
Why not build a virtual laboratory simulator?
لماذا لا نبني مختبر محاكاة افتراضي؟
Well, we did it.
حسناَ، لقد قمنا بذلك.
We basically set out to create
وضعنا أساساَ لبناء
a fully simulated, one-to-one, virtual reality laboratory simulator,
ما يحاكي بشكل كامل،و جزء بجزء، مختبر الواقع الافتراضي ،
where the students could perform experiments
حيث يمكن للطلاب إجراء التجارب
with mathematical equations
مع المعادلات الرياضية
that would simulate what would happen in a real-world lab.
التي من شأنها محاكاة مايحدث في مختبر العالم الحقيقي.
But not just simple simulations --
لكن ليس فقط محاكاة بسيطة
we would also create advanced simulations
نود أيضاَ بناء محاكاة متقدمة
with top universities like MIT,
مع أفضل الجامعات مثل معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية،
to bring out cutting-edge cancer research to these students.
لإخراج بحوث السرطان المتقدمة لهؤلاء الطلاب.
And suddenly, the universities could save millions of dollars
على نحو مفاجئ ستتمكن الجامعات أن توفر ملايين الدولارت
by letting the students perform virtual experiments
بفسح المجال للطلاب لإجراء تجارب افتراضية
before they go into the real laboratory.
قبل ذهابهم للمختبر الحقيقي.
And not only that; now, they could also understand --
و ليس ذلك فقط، ،سيتمكنوا ايضاَ من الفهم
even on a molecular level inside the machine --
حتى على المستوى الجزيئي داخل الجهاز -
what is happening to the machines.
و ما يجري في الآلات.
And then they could suddenly perform
ومن ثم يؤدوا على نحو مفاجئ
dangerous experiments in the labs as well.
تجارب خطيرة في المختبرات أيضاَ.
For instance also here,
على سبيل المثال هنا أيضاَ،
learning about salmonella bacteria, which is an important topic
التعلم عن بكتيريا السالمونيلا، وهو موضوع مهم
that many schools cannot teach for good safety reasons.
لا تستطيع معظم الجامعات تدريسه لأسباب جيدة تتعلق بالسلامة.
And we, of course, quiz the students
ونحن، بالطبع،نختبر الطلاب
and then give the teachers a full dashboard,
ومن ثم يتم إعطاء المعلمين لوحة القيادة الكاملة،
so they fully understand where the students are at.
ليتمكنوا من معرفة مستوى الطلاب في هذا.
But we didn't stop there,
ولكن لم نتوقف هنا ،
because we had seen just how important meaning is
لأننا قد رأينا فقط مدى أهمية و معنى ذلك
for the students' engagement in the class.
في مشاركة الطلاب في الصف.
So we brought in game designers
لذلك جلبنا مصممي الألعاب
to create fun and engaging stories.
لتصميم قصص ممتعة و مثيرة للإهتمام.
For instance, here in this case,
على سبيل المثال، هنا في هذه الحالة،
where the students have to solve a mysterious CSI murder case
على الطلاب حل قضية قتل سي إس آي غامضة
using their core science skills.
بإستخدام مهاراتهم في العلوم الأساسية .
And the feedback we got when we launched all of this
و ردود الأفعال التي جائتنا بعد إطلاق كل هذا
was quite overwhelmingly positive.
كان الى حد بعيد إيجابية للغاية.
Here we have 300 students,
هنا لدينا 300 طالب،
all passionately solving CSI murder cases
و كلهم يحلون قضايا قتل سي إس آي بحماسة
while learning core science skills.
مع تعلم مهارات العلوم الأساسية.
And what I love the most about this
و أكثر شيء أحببته في هذا
is really when the students come up to me sometimes afterwards,
هو حقاَ عندما يأتيني الطلاب بعد ذلك،
all surprised and a little confused,
كلهم متفاجئين ومربكين قليلاَ
and say, "I just spent two hours in this virtual lab,
و يقولون ،"أمضيت ساعتين في هذا المختبر الافتراضي،
and ... and I didn't check Facebook."
ولم أقم بفتح الفيسبوك ."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's how engaging and immersive this really is for the students.
لنتبين كم أنه جذاب و مثير لأهتمام الطلاب
And so, to investigate whether this really worked,
وهكذا،و للتحقق فيما إذا كان كل هذا يؤتي ثماره،
a learning psychologist did a study with 160 students --
طبيب نفسي مختص بالتعلم أجرى دراسة على 160 طالباَ ،
that was from Stanford University and Technical University of Denmark.
حدث هذا في جامعة ستانفورد و الجامعة التقنية في الدنمارك
And what they did is split the students into two groups.
وما قاموا به هو تقسيم الطلاب لمجموعتين
One group would only use the virtual laboratory simulations,
المجموعة الأولى ستستخدم فقط محاكاة المختبر الافتراضية،
the other group would only use traditional teaching methods,
و المجموعة الأخرى ستستخدم طرق التدريس التقليدية،
and they had the same amount of time.
وكان لديهم نفس المقدار من الوقت.
Then, interestingly,
ثم و بشكل مثير للإهتمام،
they gave the students a test before and after the experiment,
أعطوا الطلاب اختبار قبل وبعد التجربة،
so they could clearly measure the learning impact of the students.
ليتمكنوا من معرفة تأثير التعليم على الطلاب بشكل واضح.
And what they found
و ما وجدوه
was a surprisingly high 76 percent increase in the learning effectiveness
كان مدهشاَ 76 في المئة زيادة في فعالية التعلم
when using virtual laboratories over traditional teaching methods.
عند استخدام المختبرات الافتراضية على طرق التدريس التقليدية.
But even more interestingly,
أكثر من ذلك إثارة للإهتمام،
the second part of this study investigated
الجزء الثاني من هذه الدراسة التحققية
what the teacher's impact was on the learning.
و يتعلق بتأثير المعلم على العملية التدريسية.
And what they found
و ما وجدوه
was that when you combined the virtual laboratories
عندما تم جمع المختبرات الافتراضية
with teacher-led coaching and mentoring,
مع التدريب بقيادة المعلم وتوجيهه،
then we saw a total 101 percent increase in the learning effectiveness,
وجدنا ما مجموعه 101 في المئة زيادة في فعالية التعلم،
which effectively doubles the science teacher's impact
و الذي يضاعف بفعالية تأثير مدرس العلوم
with the same amount of time spent.
مع نفس مقدار الوقت التي تم قضاؤه.
So a couple of months back,
لذلك قبل شهرين،
we started asking ourselves --
بدأنا نسأل أنفسنا
we have a wonderful team now of learning psychologists
لدينا الآن فريق رائع من الأطباء النفسيين المختصين في التعلم
and teachers and scientists and game developers --
و المدرسين و العلماء و مطوري الألعاب
and we started asking ourselves:
بدأنا نسأل أنفسنا:
How can we keep ourselves to our promise
كيف نبقى على وعدنا
of constantly reimagining education?
في إعادة تصور التعليم بإستمرار؟
And today, I am really excited to be presenting what we came up with
و اليوم،أنا حقاَ متحمس لتقديم ما توصلنا إليه
and have been working incredibly hard to create.
و العمل بإستمرار على الإبتكار
I will explain briefly what this is.
سأشرح بإيجاز ما هذا.
Basically, I take my mobile phone --
بشكل أساسي،سأخذ تليفوني المحمول
most students already have these, smartphones --
معظم الطلاب لديهم مثل هذه الاجهزة الذكية
and I plug it into this virtual-reality headset, a low-cost headset.
و قمت بتوصيلته بسماعة الواقع الإفتراضي سماعة منخفضة التكلفة.
And now what I can effectively do is,
والآن ما أستطيع القيام به بفعالية،
I can literally step into this virtual world.
أنا قادرأن أخطو حرفياَ في هذا العالم الافتراضي.
We'll have some of you in the audience also get to try this,
سيكون لدينا بعض من الحضور لتجريب هذا،
because it is really something that you have to try
لأنه بالفعل شيء يجب فعلياَ تجريبه
to fully feel how immersive it really is.
لتشعر كم ستتعلق به .
It literally feels like I just stepped inside this virtual lab.
أشعر حرفياَ و كأنني أخطو داخل هذا المختبر الإفتراضي.
Do you see me up on the screen?
هل تروني على الشاشة؟
Audience: Yes.
الحضور : نعم.
Michael Bodekaer: Great! Awesome.
مايكل بوديكاير : عظيم!رائع.
So basically, I have just turned my mobile phone
جوهرياَ،فقط قمت بتحويل تليفوني المحمول
into a fully simulated, million-dollar Ivy League laboratory
لمخبر رابطة اللبلاب بقيمة مليون دولار يحاكي الواقع محاكاة تامة
with all this amazing equipment that I can interact with.
مع كل هذه المعدات الرائعة التي أستطيع التفاعل معها.
I can, for instance, pick up the pipette and do experiments with it.
يمكنني، على سبيل المثال، والتقاط ماصة والقيام بالمزيد من التجارب فيها.
I have my E-Ggel, my PCR and -- oh, look there,
لدي هنا أغراضي المخبرية، آلة ال PCR إنظروا هناك ،
I have my next-generation sequencing machine,
و هنا لدي آلة التسلسل من الجيل القادم،
and there I even have my electron microscope.
و هناك لدي أيضاَ مجهري الإلكتروني.
I mean, who's carrying around an electron microscope in their pocket?
أعني،من الذي يستطيع حمل مجهر إلكتروني في جيبه ؟
And here I have my machine,
و هنا لدي آلتي ،
I can do different experiments on the machine.
يمكنني القيام بالتجارب المختلفة على هذه الآلة.
And over here I have the door,
وهنا لدي الباب،
I can go into other experiments,
حيث يمكنني القيام بتجارب أخرى،
I can perform in the laboratories.
و اؤديها في المختبرات .
And here, I have my learning tablet.
و هنا لدي حاسوبي اللوحي التعليمي.
This is an intelligent tablet
وهو حاسوب لوحي ذكي
that allows me to read about relevant theory.
و الذي يمكنني من قراءة نظرية ذو صلة.
As you can see, I can interact with it.
كما تشاهدون ، أستطيع التفاعل معها.
I can watch videos and see content that is relevant
و أستطيع مشاهدة مقاطع الفيديو و المحتوى ذو الصلى
to the experiment that I'm performing right now.
بالتجربة التي أؤديها الآن.
Then over here, I have Marie.
وهناك، لدي ماري.
She is my teacher -- my lab assistant --
وهي معلمتي و مساعدتي في المخبر
and what she does is guides me through this whole laboratory.
وما تقوم به هو توجيهي في كامل هذا المخبر.
And very soon,
وقريباَ جداَ،
the teachers will be able to literally teleport themselves
سيكون المدرسين قادرين على نقل أنفسهم حرفياَ
into this virtual world that I'm in right now
للعالم الإفتراضي مكان وجودي في الوقت الراهن
and help me, guide me, through this whole experiment.
لمساعدتي و توجيهي،خلال كل هذه التجربة.
And now before I finalize this,
و الَآن قبل أن أنهي هذا،
I want to show you an even cooler thing, I think --
أريد أن أطلعكم على شيء أكثر تميزاَ، في إعتقادي
something you cannot even do in real laboratories.
شيء لا يمكنك القيام به في المختبرات الحقيقية.
This is a PCR machine.
هذه آلة الPCR.
I'm now going to start this experiment.
سأبدأ الآن بتجربة.
And what I just did is literally shrunk myself a million times
و ماقمت به حرفياَ هو تصغير نفسي ملايين المرات
into the size of a molecule --
إلى حجم الجزيء
and it really feels like it, you have to try this.
وهذا شعور يجب أن تجربه،
So now it feels like I'm standing inside the machine
و يبدو الأمر كأنني داخل الآلة
and I'm seeing all the DNA, and I see the molecules.
وأشاهد كل الحموض النووية، وأشاهد الجزيئات.
I see the polymerase and the enzymes and so forth.
أشاهد البوليميراز و الانزيمات و هكذا دواليك.
And I can see how in this case,
و أستطيع مشاهدة في هذه الحالة،
DNA is being replicated millions of times,
كيف يتم توليد الحمض النووي ملايين المرات،
just like it's happening inside your body right now.
بشكل مشابه لما يحدث في جسمك الآن.
And I can really feel and understand how all of this works.
و أستطيع أن أشعر و أفهم كيف يعمل كل هذا.
Now, I hope that gives you a little bit of a sense
الآن ، أمل أن يعطيك هذا فكرة بسيطة و أن تدرك
of the possibilities in these new teaching methods.
إمكانيات الطرق الجديدة في التعليم.
And I want to also emphasize
وأريد أن أؤكد أيضاَ
that everything you just saw also works on iPads and laptops
أن كل شيء رأيتموه يعمل على الحاسوب المحمول و الآيباد أيضاَ
without the headsets.
و بدون سماعات.
I say that for a very important reason.
أقول ذلك لسبب مهم جداَ.
In order for us to really empower and inspire
ليتسنى لنا تمكين و إلهام
the next generation of scientists,
الجيل القادم من العلماء،
we really need teachers to drive the adoption
نحن بحاجة لمعلمين لقيادة إعتماد
of new technologies in the classroom.
التكنولوجيا الجديدة في الفصول الدراسية.
And so in many ways,
لذلك و بعدة طرق،
I believe that the next big, quantum leap in science education
أعتقد أن النقلة النوعية الكبيرة القادمة في تعليم العلوم،
lies no longer with the technology,
لا تعتمد على التكنولوجيا ،
but rather with the teachers' decision
بقدر إعتمادها على قرار المعلم
to push forward and adopt these technologies
لدفع واعتماد هذه التقنيات
inside the classrooms.
في الفصول الدراسية.
And so it is our hope that more universities and schools and teachers
لذلك فأملنا أن المزيد من الجامعات و المدارس و المعلمين
will collaborate with technology companies
سيتعاونوا مع شركات التكنولوجيا
to realize this full potential.
لتحقيق هذه الإمكانات الكاملة.
And so,
لذلك،
lastly, I'd like to leave you with a little story
أخيراَ، أود ترككم مع قصة قصيرة
that really inspires me.
ألهمتني للغاية.
And that is the story of Jack Andraka.
و هي قصة جاك أندريكا .
Some of you might already know him.
بعض منكم ربما يعرفه.
Jack invented a new, groundbreaking low-cost test for pancreatic cancer
اخترع جاك إختبارمنخفض التكلفة وهو حجر الأساس للكشف عن سرطان البنكرياس
at the age 15.
و هو في سن ال15 .
And when Jack shares his story of how he did this huge breakthrough,
وعندما أخبر جاك قصته وكيف وصل لهذا الإنجاز الضخم،
he also explains that one thing almost prevented him
قام أيضاً بشرح أن هناك شيء واحد منعه
from making this breakthrough.
من التوصل لهذا الإنجاز.
And that was that he did not have access to real laboratories,
و هو عدم قدرته للوصول للمختبرات الحقيقية،
because he was too inexperienced
لأنه لا يتمتع بالخبرة الكافية
to be allowed in.
ليتم السماح له بذلك.
Now, imagine if we could bring
الآن ،تصوروا إذا كان بإمكاننا توفير
Ivy League, million-dollar virtual laboratories
مختبرات رابطة اللبلاب الإفتراضية بقيمة المليون دولار
out to all these students just like Jack,
لكل هؤلاء الطلاب أمثال جاك
all over the world,
حول العالم،
and give them the latest, greatest, most fancy machines you can imagine
و منحهم أحدث و أعظم وأفخر الآلات الممكن تصورها
that would quite literally make any scientist in here
و التي من شأنها جعل أي عالم في هذا المجال
jump up and down out of pure excitement.
القفز صعوداَ و هبوطاَ من الإثارة والحماس
And then imagine how that would empower and inspire
وبعدها تصوروا كيف سيمكن هذا و يلهم
a whole new generation of young and bright scientists,
جيل جديد كلياَ من العلماء الشباب والمشرقين،
ready to innovate and change the world.
ليصبحوا جاهزين على إبتكار و تغيير العالم.
Thank you very much.
شكراَ جزيلاَ.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)